All right, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, today's דף daf is פ"ז Peis
Zayin and פז, Paz,
exactly,
it's a golden דף.
daf. So, in the גאלדענע מדינה. Goldene Medine. All right, so we
pick up with the גמרא Gemara at the very last line of
פ"ו עמוד ב. Peis Vav Amud Beis. We've just dealt with the
idea that a husband whose wife is working in his store can
make his wife take an oath that she hasn't done fiddled around
with the books,
misappropriated any
funds, and then we dealt with the next משנה Mishnah that says
that a husband can also write for his wife at the time
of the כתובה, Kesubah, presumably and other times, but it sounds like
from the גמרא's Gemara going to assume that this is at the
time they're getting married, that he basically exempts her from ever having
to make a נדר Neder or a שבועה. Shvua. שבועה Shvua is
a direct oath, 'I didn't steal any money.' A נדר Neder would
be 'If I stole any money or misappropriated anything, let all of
the fruit in the world, for example, be forbidden to me.' And
then the משנה Mishnah played out the difference about when that oath
includes also her heirs or his heirs and so on. Let's take
a look at the גמרא. Gemara. Last line on פ"ו עמוד ב.
Peis Vav Amud Beis. שבועה מאי עבידתיה? Shvua mai avidatei? Why is
he exempting her from a שבועה? Shvua? What type of a שבועה
Shvua are we talking about? So, אמר רב יהודה אמר רב: Amar
Rav Yehuda Amar Rav: על אפוטרופיא שנעשית בחיי בעלה. Al apitropaya shenasit
bechayei ba'ala. It's referring back to the previous משנה. Mishnah. It's basically
anticipating
that she was going to be in charge of the store or
the business and therefore at the time of the marriage he already
waived and exempted her from any שבועה. Shvua. רב נחמן אמר רבה
בר אבוה, Rav Nachman Amar Rabba Bar Avuha, רב נחמן Rav Nachman
says in the name of רבה בר אבוה: Rabba Bar Avuha: No.
על פוגמת כתובתה. Al pogemes kesuvasah. It's not referencing the previous משנה,
Mishnah, it's referencing the following משנה. Mishnah. If you take a look
down at the bottom of the page here, about three lines, four
lines before the lines get wide where there's a next משנה. Mishnah.
It says: הפוגמת כתובתה לא תפרע אלא בשבועה. Hapogemes kesuvasah lo tipara
ela bishvua. See that line? So, that's the next משנה. Mishnah. So
what does that mean? פוגם Pogem means
to injure or
to cut into. So basically what happens is a woman comes to
collect her כתובה Kesubah and the husband said 'I paid it.' So
she said 'No you didn't' and 'Here's my כתובה' Kesubah and 'You
don't have any proof you paid it' and fine, then she collects.
But let's say it's a type of a מודה במקצת. modeh bemiktzas.
Let's say she says 'Yeah, fine, you paid a hundred out of
the thousand, but you still owe me the rest of the nine
hundred.' She didn't have to say that, but she did. So she
herself is פוגמת, pogemes, she injures as it were her כתובה, Kesubah,
she admits that the amount is not full. And in that case,
once she concedes that some of it's been paid, she has to
take an oath that the rest of it has not been paid,
that the rest of it is still outstanding. Okay, so we'll discuss
that in a משנה Mishnah when we get to the next משנה.
Mishnah. What?
Isn't there a מיגו migo she could have said nothing?
Yeah, מיגו migo she could have said nothing, whatever, we'll discuss it,
okay? So that's coming up. But for now you just have to
know that that's a case that she has to make a שבועה.
Shvua. So he says that that's the case, that he basically says
at the time of the marriage 'If you ever come to collect
your כתובה Kesubah and for some reason part of it's been paid
off or whatever, I'm going to waive you from ever having to
make a שבועה Shvua that the rest has not been paid.' Okay,
so that's what he says. Now, the גמרא Gemara רש"י Rashi spells
out that it's not just two different scenarios, there's probably a halachic
debate between them. And the halachic debate is the following: is that
if you say it applies to the case of the storekeeper, fine,
I'll make you a storekeeper, I'm going to waive ahead of time,
whatever, that you won't have to take a שבועה. Shvua. But if
it's the case about פוגמת, pogemes, it's not so obvious that if
I waive it that includes the case of פוגמת. pogemes.
Because, A, you could say that the case of פוגמת pogemes maybe
is one that there's already some
circumstantial some basis, not to assume that she's lying, but some basis
to assume there might be a problem. Number one. And number two,
as רש"י Rashi says, פוגמת pogemes she sort of did it to
herself. I didn't impose the שבועה Shvua on her. I didn't say
'Oh, I think you're cheating on the books, you have to take
an oath to me.' In the פוגמת, pogemes, once she concedes that
it was paid, that sort of triggers
her obligation. So maybe that's not included when I say I won't
demand a שבועה. Shvua. I'm not demanding a שבועה. Shvua. What? It's
the court. Right, maybe that's a good way of thinking about it.
It's the court that's demanding. So maybe if you say maybe if
you say that it's the case of אפוטרופיא apitropaya you would not
this would not cover the case of פוגמת. pogemes. That maybe wouldn't
be included in the waiving. Okay, so maybe there's a halachic debate
between them. So let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. אזל
רב מרדכי, Azal Rav Mordechai, so רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai went. אמר
ליה שמעתא קמיה דרב אשי. Amar le shmata kamei de Rav Ashi.
He told over this discussion in front of רב אשי. Rav Ashi.
This debate about what the משנה Mishnah means.
And here was the ensuing discussion. דישלמא למאן דאמר Dishlama leman de'amar
על פוגמת כתובתה, al pogemes kesuvasah, if
the משנה Mishnah is saying that he's waiving the obligation of a
שבועה Shvua and that refers to or includes the case of פוגמת,
pogemes, so did we understand why you would do that at the
beginning of the marriage? דאסקא דעתה, De'aska da'atei,
because it occurs to her, the possibility arises she considers the possibility,
דילמא מצטריכי לי זוזי, dilma mitzrechi li zuzei,
maybe at some time in the marriage I'll need to take an
advance on my כתובה. Kesubah.
and I'll take some of the money out of my כתובה, kesubah,
I'll take an advance on my כתובה. kesubah. ואמינא ve'amina so and
I'm afraid that then when it comes the time to collect the
כתובה, kesubah, if I get divorced or widowed, that I'll have to
make a שבועה shevua about it. ואמרה ליה va'amra lei and so
she says to her husband, כתוב לי דלא משבעת לי, ksov li
delo mashvasli, write for me that you won't make me take an
oath if that ever happens. So the possibility that there might be
a future scenario of פוגמת כתובתה pogemes kesuvosa occurs to her, and
she might ask her husband to waive the requirement of a שבועה
shevua for that. That's a reasonable scenario.
Why would he want to do that?
Because he wants to get married. Why does anybody want to ever
sign a prenuptial agreement that gives up some of their rights? Because
that's what the other side is asking and demanding.
Okay, so why is it called פוגמת כתובתה, pogemes kesuvosa, the earlier
payout of part of the כתובה? kesubah?
Yeah, because it's full and you're cutting into
it, dipping into it.
Yeah, exactly. Okay. So, okay,
so therefore that's a reasonable scenario about why somebody would write this
at the beginning of the marriage. אלא מאן דאמר אפוטרופא שנעשית בחיי
בעלה, ela man d'amar apitropsha shenasis bechayei ba'ala,
but in the case of a woman that was appointed in her
husband's life as a type of, you know, executor—not trustee, trustee's the
wrong word, but executor, or you know,
administrator—thank you, administrator or, right,
power of attorney.
Exactly. Anyway, somebody in charge of the husband's business. But, אלא מאן
דאמר Ela man d'amar אפוטרופא שנעשית בחיי בעלה, apitropsha shenasis bechayei ba'ala,
אי הוה ידעה דמותיב אפוטרופא? ee hava yad'a demoseiv apitropsha?
Why would it occur to her that he would have made her,
put her in that position, דאמר ליה de'amar lei that she should
say to him ahead of time, כתוב לי דלא משבעת לי, ksov
li delo mashvasli, right, you know, write for me that you won't
make me take an oath. So that's a weird scenario. Now, of
course, how really weird is it? So תוספות Tosafos says, look at
תוספות, Tosafos, ואלא מאן דאמר וכו' ve'ela man d'amar etc. תוספות Tosafos
says, ואין להקשות דלדידי איכא לאוקמה מתניתין כשיכבר אפוטרופא. ve'ein lehaksheos d'leidadei
ika le'ukma masnisin keshikvar apitropsha. Maybe,
you know, that's how they met. He had hired her as the
manager and they met and they fell in love and now they're
getting married and he wants her to stay on as the manager,
right? I mean, you can think of a lot of scenarios. You
know, you can think that he's got a store and he says,
oh, it'd be great and then you'll work in the store and
I'll go out and I'll, I don't know, I'll buy the produce
and you'll, you know, you'll run the store while I'm away. So
you can imagine lot of scenarios where she's already the manager. Whatever.
Well, right, but either she's already in the job or even if
she's not in the job, he knows what business he has and
they're already talking about how they're going to run the business together.
So you can imagine a lot of scenarios. Anyway, the גמרא Gemara
thinks that that's not פשט. pshat. Okay, that would not be a
standard case. It's not the first time or last time that we're
going to talk, say the משנה's Mishna in a non-standard case. Anyway,
that's the question. So the גמרא, Gemara, so let's see what the
answer was. אמר ליה, Amar lei, so he said back to him,
אתון, atun, you, because this was רב מרדכי Rav Mordechai telling this
over to רב אשי. Rav Ashi. So רב אשי Rav Ashi said,
אתון אהא מתניתו לה. atun haha masnisula. You teach this line of
רב יהודה Rav Yehuda אפוטרופא שנעשית בחיי בעלה apitropsha shenasis bechayei ba'ala
and you say that it's coming to explain the scenario of the
משנה. Mishna. And then you want to say that's a bizarre scenario.
But אנן, anan, we, אהא מתנינן לה. haha masninan lah. We don't
teach this line—thank you, we don't teach this line on the משנה.
Mishna. רב נחמן Rav Nachman says the משנה Mishna is talking about
פוגמת כתובתה pogemes kesuvosa and everybody agrees to that. Why are you
waiving the נדר neder and the שבועה? shevua? To anticipate a case
of פוגמת כתובתה. pogemes kesuvosa. And everybody would agree that even though
that's something that comes about because she herself is פוגמת pogemes or
whatever, that's included when he says I'm not going to make you
swear. Everybody agrees that's פשט pshat in the משנה. Mishna. The line
that said אפוטרופא apitropsha in her husband's life wasn't said to explain
the משנה. Mishna. What was it said? אנן אהא מתנינן לה. anan
haha masnisan lah. We say that it was coming to explain not
the beginning of the משנה, Mishna, but the end of the משנה.
Mishna. What did the end of the משנה Mishna say? הלכה מקבר
בעלה לבית אביה. Halcha mikever ba'ala leveit aviha. She left the burying
her husband and went to her father's house. או שחזרה לבית חמיה.
O shechazra leveit chamia. Or returned to her father-in-law's house. ולא נעשית
אפוטרופא Velo nasis apitropsha and she has not been now made, now
that her husband is dead, she no longer—thank you—is the, what do
you say the word was? The manager, the administrator. אין היורשים משביעין
אותה. Eino yoresh mashpi'in osa. So if the husband had exempted her
and his heirs from imposing any oath on her, so then they
can't make her swear, the heirs can't make her swear on the
stuff in the past. But ואם נעשית אפוטרופא, ve'im nasis apitropsha, but
if now she continues in this role of being an administrator, then
היורשים משביעין אותה על העתיד לבוא. yoresh mashpi'in osa al hasid lavo.
The heirs can make her swear on the new, you know, future
business aspects. אבל אין משביעין אותה על מה שעבר, Aval ein mashpi'in
osa al she'avar, but not on, you know, past business activities. So
therefore, the husband was able to exempt her from any oath that
she would have had to make for dealings when, for you know,
for when it was his business. And therefore he can say that
my heirs can't make you swear on anything you did for me
while I was alive, any of the activities you did while I
was alive. But after he died, if she continues to work for
the heirs now, that's a new deal. And then the heirs, that's
her obligation directly to the heirs. And then they can make her
swear for the new stuff. Okay, that's the משנה. Mishnah. And now
here's the question that we asked on the משנה. Mishnah. שעבר
מה עבידתיה? She'avar ma avidateh? So what's going on about the past,
which basically means how far in the past, you know, what when
it says they can make her swear by the past, how much
of the past? They can't, I'm sorry, thank you, they cannot make
her swear on the past, thank you, they can only make her
swear on the future, how much of the past are we talking
about? So let's take a look, what's the question? So here's the
question. אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, so
here is the statement that we said a minute ago of אמר
רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, not explaining the
first case of the משנה, Mishnah, explaining this case of the past.
And אמר רב יהודה אמר רב, Amar Rav Yehuda Amar Rav, על
אפוטרופיא שנעשית בחיי הבעל, al epitrofaya shenasais bechayei habaal, that they cannot
make her swear on any of the business dealings she did when
her husband was alive. Okay, isn't that obvious? No, here's his point.
אבל בין מיתה לקבורה משביעינן לה. Aval bein misa likvura mashpinan lah.
How about the fact that who's running the store during the period
of אנינות, aninus, I guess? Okay, so or
as the גמרא's Gemara going to say in a minute, let's say
she actually has
to, let's say,
well yes, she is an אנינה, aninah, she's running the store.
Sorry, I gotta go, I gotta open up.
I know, the איסור מלאכה issur melacha only applies by אבילות, aveilus,
not by אנינות, aninus, but more important is we're going to see,
is she might actually have to sell off some things in order
to raise some money for the קבורה. kvura. Okay,
so technically that's the heirs' estate now. So technically that's עתיד לבוא,
atid lavo, that's her relationship to the heirs, not her relationship to
the, right, not the business dealings of the husband's estate, now it
actually is the heirs' estate. Okay, so he says yes, so that's
now the heirs' estate and therefore they can make her take an
oath that she handled things properly between death and burial.
So the משנה's Mishnah talking about like the very rare case where
she's actually running a store while
her husband's sitting there rotting in his, you know, what are you
talking about? No. He's been running the store for the last ten
years. The husband never made her take an oath, he totally trusted
her. He died. Now the heirs say, yeah, you had our father
fooled. We know you've been cheating for the last ten years. Make
us take an oath. So they can't do that. Because the husband
already exempted him and his heirs from making her take an oath.
Okay, but they can, if she continues to run the store, they
can make her take an oath. Can they make her take an
oath on any business she did between the death and the burial?
No, I know, but so you're saying that only like that that
משנה Mishnah is taking is coming,
not only, when it says they cannot make her take an oath
on the past but on the future, so clearly, okay, here's ten
years that he's alive, right, I understand, okay, then he dies. That's
her? Yeah, no, here, he's dead. Okay, then, okay, then here he's
buried. Okay, she's dancing on his, okay fine.
Okay, and then they continue. Okay, so it says no oath here,
she can't be נשבע על שעבר, nishba al she'avar, yes they can
make her be נשבע nishba here. That's what the משנה Mishnah says.
The משנה Mishnah is telling you this period of time they can't
make her to be נשבע, nishba, this period of time they can,
and all we want to know is this period of time, is
it included in the no or is it included in the yes?
Okay,
it's a simple question.
Yes, is
it, is it, is it she would say to him at some
point, just don't make me take an oath for pious reasons? In
other words, a general,
it could be, but it sounds more that it's a trust issue,
not a pious issue. Okay.
In other words, I need you to trust me. Yeah, you can
make me take an oath.
Exactly. Okay. So that's the question. So now when רב יהודה אמר
רב Rav Yehuda Amar Rav says אפוטרופיא שנעשית בחיי הבעל, epitrofaya shenasais
bechayei habaal, he's not describing the basic scenario of waiving the oath
like we thought. He's not going on the רישא Reisha of the
משנה. Mishnah. He's saying the סיפא Seifa where it says when she
is exempt, he's underscoring only while the husband was alive. אבל בין
מיתה לקבורה משביעינן לה. Aval bein misa likvura mashpinan lah. But between
death and burial, then she's working for the heirs and they can
make her take an oath. רב מתנא אמר אמר,
Rav
Masna
Amar Amar, אפילו בין מיתה לקבורה לא משביעינן לה.
afilu bein misa likvura
lo mashpinan lah. No,
even though technically she's working for the heirs, they cannot make her
take an oath during that period of death between death and burial.
Why? What's the logic? דאמרינן דנהרדעי De'amrinan de'Nahardei because Nahardai says, לכרגא
ולמזוני ולקבורה, lekarga u'lemezonei u'lekvura,
for the purpose of paying a poll tax, or for מזוני mezonei
in order for let's say food because this is basically a guy
died. And now the government wants its poll tax, and if you
don't pay the government on time, there's going to be heavy fines
and consequences. Or the אלמנה almanah needs her food. Or Rashi says
maybe the heirs need their food, but let's say the אלמנה almanah
needs her food. Or קבורה, kvura, the guy needs to be buried
and all these things is you need to sell property from the
estate. after the guy died to handle these things. Okay. In these
cases, מזבנינן בלא אכרזתא, mazbininan belo achrazta,
we sell without going through making any announcement. Okay, like you know,
right? You know, you know that in the, in the newspapers, right?
You know, where they have a state, you have to make an
announcement that certain property is up for sale or whatever, and then
people, the public, have to be informed a good deal ahead of
time so that, so that the, right, so that, so that the
people can get a reasonably, reasonably price, good price for whatever, for
what they're selling. So that's true too. If the heirs, you have
to sell property from the heirs' estate, from the, and to pay
off certain debts or whatever, you don't just סתם stam immediately liquidate
it. You have to make announcements and go through a period that
takes time and lets people know that it's available for sale. But
if there are certain things that are pressing and have to be
taken care of immediately, and else either it'll be consequential like, you
know, the government won't get their taxes and that's going to really
hurt the heirs and the estate, or people are going to really
be hurt like the woman won't have food to put on her
table, the אלמנה, almanah, or the guy isn't going to get the
burial he deserves, then you just sell them as quickly as possible,
you don't go through this process. That's the teaching. Now how's that
relevant? So רש"י Rashi says that's relevant because basically it shows that
there's a certain urgency to take care of the burial and do
things. And the woman basically says, I'm not going to have to
take, if you make me take an oath that I handled everything
perfectly during this period of selling the money to handle the קבורה,
kvurah, like, you know,
sometimes you make, you know, like, you know, not the best decisions
because you just got to get the funds quickly. So I'm not
going to have to take an oath, oh, oh, I sold it
to this guy and I should have, and I lost money and
I should have sold it to somebody else and I cheated the
business or whatever. I had to do certain things in order to
raise the money for the business, so it's not fair to impose
an oath on the dealings, right, to raise money for the burial.
It's not fair to impose an oath for the dealings I had
to do during that time. That time you're going to have to,
it's going to have to be a little sloppy. That's what רש"י
Rashi says. תוספות Tosafot says, one minute, fine, you can't make her
take an oath that she, let's say, made the best decisions, but
you can still make her take an oath that she didn't pocket
any money, right? So that they can say, fine, you know, we're
not allowed to make you take an oath that, like, you know,
that you handled everything, you know, as best as possible, but we
can make you take an oath that you didn't steal any money.
So תוספות, Tosafot, right, so why not? So תוספות Tosafot says no.
So the real point is
that we're afraid that she's going to say, look, until now, the
last 10 years, she's been doing the business because she hasn't had
to take an oath. If we're going to tell her you're going
to have to take an oath for any dealings you do now
to raise the money for your husband's funeral, what's she going to
do?
Goodbye!
I'm not handling that. The whole reason I'm willing to handle these
funds is because I don't have to take an oath. You want
me to take an oath for this? You guys handle it. Goodbye!
Okay. And then the heirs are going to be left with all
this estate that they've never dealt with or whatever. So one way
or another, because of the urgency of burial, we have basically a
policy position that we can't make her take an oath even though
technically they should be entitled. That's the debate. Okay. Now, I want
to say one thing and then I'll take Rabbi Dubbs' question, which
is, this is also, by the way, fascinating in terms of, like,
the whole history of, like, source criticism of the תלמוד Talmud and
the academic sort of way of sort of seeing, like, you know,
because a lot of that approach to the גמרא Gemara says, like,
okay, here's the statement, and the גמרא Gemara sort of gives it
this context and explanation, but maybe that wasn't how the statement was
originally intended. Maybe it was originally said in a different context. You
know, so that's often like a question that academics ask. Well, look
at what happened here. We had the משנה. Mishnah. The גמרא Gemara
posed us with two positions which seem to be talking to one
another and debating the first line of the משנה. Mishnah. Is it
talking about אפוטרופא שנעשה בחיי בעל epitropos shenasah bechayey baal or is
it talking about פוגמת כתובתה? pogemet ketubatah? And they were put side
by side as competing explanations for the beginning of the משנה. Mishnah.
And then the גמרא Gemara says, actually, this statement, אפוטרופא, epitropos, was
never said relating to this other statement. They were never in conversation.
And it was never at the beginning of the משנה. Mishnah. This
statement about פוגמת, pogemet, that was the only statement that existed at
the beginning of the משנה Mishnah that everybody agreed to, and this
statement was actually part of a different debate down here at the
end of the משנה Mishnah about this period between מיתה misah and
קבורה. kvurah. So I think it's like really just interesting that the
גמרא Gemara sort of shows you how it sort of misunderstood, you
know,
or mispositioned, like, and that actually it was, he went to tell
רב אשי Rav Ashi about this debate. Who was it? רב אשי?
Rav Ashi?
Yeah, רב אשי. Rav Ashi. And רב אשי Rav Ashi says, no,
you guys, you applied that statement to the beginning. You didn't understand.
That statement was meant at the end. So it's like interesting. It
shows you that, right, that sometimes there's not always this great clarity.
You know, somebody said something on the משנה, Mishnah, but exactly what
the context was and what he was answering and who he was
talking to wasn't always totally clear. Yes.
But shouldn't we be afraid, let's say it's יתומים קטנים, yetomim ketanim,
and then they're going to say, okay, well, the past 10 years
while Dad was alive, I never had to do anything, and now
that
Dad's dead, should I forget? I'm going to go. And then meanwhile,
like, the יתומים yetomim are left without anyone managing the store.
So let the בית דין Beis Din go and...
it's the same thing... what? Right. So they didn't, so they didn't,
so they won't get involved then, I guess, or...
Yeah, but then it's not the urgency of making sure the guy
gets buried. True.
Do you have anything to say about the fact that since antiquity
funerals are so costly? Like, it's counterintuitive. You know what I mean?
What, it's counterintuitive?
Yeah, you get a bunch of guys
together, this is the way you show your last respects, I don't
know, we're not going to talk about that now. Okay, we'll do
it when we do מועד קטן. Moed Katan. All right, so the
משנה Mishnah says like this.
Okay, you saw
fifty years from now?
Oh, five years, five years. Okay, anyway. All right, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like
this: אמר רבה. Amar Rabbah. אמר רבה אמר רב חייא. Amar Rabbah
amar Rav Chiya. דלא נדר Dela neder או o דלא שבועה. dela
shvuah. So if somebody says without a נדר neder and without a
שבועה, shvuah, that's the... he doesn't say, right, what is the language
he uses? It's the משנה Mishnah says נדר ושבועה אין לי עליך.
neder ushvuah ein li alaich. Okay, and then the question was עליך,
alaich, but does that mean על שייך לי, al shayach li, does
it mean your שייך? shayach? Right, the whole משנה Mishnah was whether
the language included also her heirs, his heirs. That's when he says
אין לי עליך. ein li alaich. Let's say he talks in the
more passive language, it'll be without a נדר, neder, דלא נדר. dela
neder. Okay.
When I first went to Israel, I had to learn, I had
to learn the modern Hebrew word of ללא, lilo, right? ללא, lilo,
without. Like when you learn גמרא Gemara or whatever, it's בלי. bli.
Right? ללא lilo is, I think, modern Hebrew. Anyway, דלא. dela. דלא
dela is sort of like ללא, lilo, without. Okay. Without a נדר,
neder, דלא נדר, דלא שבועה. dela neder dela shvuah. No... without a
נדר neder and without a שבועה. shvuah. הוא אינו יכול להשביע. hu
eino yachol l’hashbia. That means that he can't make her take it,
אבל יורשין משביעין אותה. aval yorshin mashbi'in osah. That is not a
strong enough language, meaning it's not clear one way or the other
way, so we interpret it narrowly. It's not a strong enough language
which
gets... and that the heirs cannot make her take an oath. The
heirs can make her take an oath. Okay? אבל יורשין משביעין אותה.
aval yorshin mashbi'in osah. נקי נדר נקי שבועה. Naki neder naki shvuah.
If you'll be clean from a נדר, neder, clean from a שבועה.
shvuah. So the sense of being clean means totally free. It's not
just I won't impose it. בין הוא בין יורשיו אין משביעין אותה.
Bein hu bein yorshav ein mashbi'in osah. Then neither he nor his
heirs can make her take an oath. הכי קאמר לה. Hachi ka'amar
lah. This is what he's saying to her: מנקיש משבועתא. minakish mishvuasa.
I have cleansed you from any need of any שבועה. shvuah. So
to be totally clean means that there will never be a need
for it.
רב יוסף? Rav Yosef? What? Can he do that? Can he impose
that on his heirs?
Well again, on his heirs for business, business activities she did when
he was alive. Okay, for old stuff. Yes. Okay. רב יוסף אמר
רב חייא. Rav Yosef amar Rav Chiya. So רב יוסף Rav Yosef
says in the name of רב חייא: Rav Chiya: דלא נדר dela
neder, דלא שבועה. dela shvuah. הוא אינו יכול להשביע ויורשין משביעין אותה.
hu eino yachol l’hashbia v’yorshin mashbi'in osah.
I agree with you, when he says without a נדר, neder, he
can't make her take an oath but the heirs can. נקי נדר
נקי שבועה, Naki neder naki shvuah, but as opposed to the language
of clean from a נדר, neder, clean from a שבועה, shvuah, בין
הוא בין יורשין משביעין אותה. bein hu bein yorshin mashbi'in osah. That
actually doesn't exempt her from anything. He and... both he and his
heirs can make her take an oath. הכי קאמר. Hachi ka'amar. And
here's how I'm going to read that language: לה נקי נפשך בשבועתא.
lah naki nafshach b’shvuasa. You will have to prove your own innocence
through taking a שבועה. shvuah. Of course, and then why is he
bothered to write it? I mean, that would be a real way
that somebody could, you know, trick their wives because you would assume
that if somebody's writing it, he's coming to change the status quo.
This is just reaffirming the status quo. And that's also interesting that
we don't use the reality that you're actually writing something to assume
like it's sort of like אין אדם מוציא דבריו לבטלה. ein adam
motzi d'varav livatalah. If that's all you're saying, why do you say
anything? Okay, so that's a pretty harsh read of it.
Yeah, you have to be... you have to be careful. It doesn't
say נקי מנדר. naki mineder.
I understand, but still, why are you writing it? If that's the
הלכה halacha anyway?
Okay. Good marriage is based on trust.
Exactly. שלח רב זכאי למר עוקבא. Shelach Rav Zakai l’Mar Ukva. So
רב זכאי Rav Zakai sent to מר עוקבא: Mar Ukva: בין דלא
שבועה בין דנקי שבועה, bein dela shvuah bein dinaki shvuah, whether you
use the language without an oath, whether you use the language clean
from an oath, בין דלא נדר בין דנקי נדר, bein dela neder
bein dinaki neder, or whether by the vow, בנכסיי... b’nichsai... בנכסיי... b’nichsai...
הוא אינו יכול להשביע אבל יורשין משביעין אותה מנכסיי... hu eino yachol
l’hashbia aval yorshin mashbi'in osah minichsai... I'm sorry, that doesn't matter. There's
no difference between
what language you use. Here's the only difference that it matters. If
he says בנכסיי, b’nichsai, that I... you've clean from a neder with
my property, הוא אינו יכול להשביע אבל יורשין משביעין אותה. hu eino
yachol l’hashbia aval yorshin mashbi'in osah. He can't, but this possessive my
means the heirs can. Even though that when she did the business
dealings it was his, but once it's no longer his, the heirs
can make her take an oath on those past business dealings. If
he says מנכסייא אילין, minichsaya ilin, if he says from this property,
he doesn't use the possessive my, בין הוא בין יורשין אין משביעין
אותה. bein hu bein yorshin ein mashbi'in osah. Then neither he nor
his heirs can... so what if he says neither מנכסיי minichsai or
מנכסייא אילין? minichsaya ilin? Presumably then it would be that the heirs
cannot. He's basically saying it doesn't matter which language you use. The
only thing that would limit it to him would be if you
use the possessive my property. If you didn't use the possessive my
property, then it includes the heirs. Okay. Only that they can't...
they can't make her
take an oath.
Are we saying this is always about the stuff in the past?
Okay. Now, בין הוא בין יורשין אין משביעין אותה. Bein hu bein
yorshin ein mashbi'in osah. אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל משום אבא שאול
בן אימא מרים. Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel mishum Abba Shaul ben
Ima Miriam. So רב
נחמן Rav Nachman in the name of שמואל Shmuel in the name
of אבא שאול. Abba Shaul. the son of אימא מרים, Ima Miriam,
interesting, name of his mother here. בין דלא שבועה בין דנקי שבועה
בין דלא נדר בין דנקי נדר בין דנכסי בין דנכסי איהו, Bein
d'la shavua bein d'naki shavua bein d'la neder bein d'naki neder bein
d'nichsai bein d'nichsai ihu, whatever language you use, even if you use
the possessive my property, בין הוא בין יורשיו אין משביעין אותה. Bein
hu bein yorshav ein mashpi'in osah. So you cannot make her take
an oath. So this is very much like broadening the protection of
the woman as opposed to the משנה Mishnah that had all of
these distinctions, עליך ועל יורשיך, alaich v'al yorshaich, right, עלי, alai, אין
לי עליך. ein li alaich. If you use any of these other
languages not in the משנה Mishnah that are somewhat ambiguous, we will
interpret them in the maximum way to protect the woman and to
say she doesn't have to take an oath. But that's in theory.
In practice, okay, אבל מה אעשה, aval mah e'eseh, what can I
do, שהרי אמרו חכמים הבא ליפרע מנכסי יתומים לא יפרע אלא בשבועה,
sheharei amru chachamim haba lifra minichsei yesomim lo yifra ela b'shvuah, that
anybody, any creditor that comes to collect from the heirs has to
take an oath that the debt has not been paid up. Okay,
so therefore he basically says look, in terms of the there are
two types of שבועות shvuos that could be made here. One is
the שבועה shvuah of somebody who managed my business that I can
make them take a שבועה shvuah that they didn't steal anything. That
the heirs cannot make her take a שבועה shvuah about. Okay. However,
there's another שבועה, shvuah, which is that which is that anybody who
comes to collect money from the heirs, because the heirs don't know
all the business dealings of the father or whatever, has to take
an oath that that that the debt has not been paid. Okay,
so therefore the father cannot exempt her from that oath, that's not
an oath obligated to him, right, the oath obligated to him is
about the business dealings. So if the case was can't if he
says this language, can they make her take an oath that that
she didn't steal any money from the business when the father was
alive? No, they can't. So the case of אפוטרופוס apitropas is covered.
But you remember we're also dealing with the case of פוגמת כתובתה,
pogemes ksuvasah, right, that's another case. So let's say he says this
language. So if he was alive and she came to collect her
כתובה ksuvah and she said a hundred had been paid off, okay,
he said this language, he can't make her take an oath. Now
he's dead and the heir she comes to collect this from the
heirs. So in terms of the normal requirement of פוגמת כתובתה pogemes
ksuvasah have to make a שבועה, shvuah, you don't have to make
a שבועה, shvuah, the dad already exempted you from that. But you
know why you have to make a שבועה? shvuah? Because anybody who's
coming to collect any debt from heirs is required to make a
שבועה. shvuah. All right, so you get it, this language works, but
it only works for the oath obligated to the father. It only
works for the oath of the storekeeper, it only works for the
oath of פוגמת כתובתה, pogemes ksuvasah, but there are some scenarios, like
coming to collect a כתובה, ksuvah, even if it wasn't פוגמת כתובתה,
pogemes ksuvasah, which has nothing to do with responsibility to father, anybody
who comes to collect a debt from the heirs has to has
to make a
שבועה shvuah and she's now being conceptualized by the חכמים chachamim as
a creditor.
Yeah, it doesn't matter, money is owed her. It doesn't matter whether
it came through a loan or what what it came from.
So in other words she's now being she's a creditor and the
כתובה ksuvah is a debt and she's coming to collect and to
collect it so
she's got to be treated like any other creditor.
Exactly. Fine, you're not a פוגמת כתובתה, pogemes ksuvasah, that obligation is
waived. Who cares? You're coming to collect money from us, you gotta
make a שבועה.
shvuah. And is he allowed to write a specific clause though exempting
her from that?
No, that is an obligation that the heir that's about between her
and the heirs. Okay.
So to say that they didn't receive payment.
Exactly. And the oath is that none of it has been paid
and she didn't receive this money.
Okay.
Okay. איכא דאמרי, Ika d'amri, some say איכא דאמרי לא מתניתא, ika
d'amri la masnisa, that this wasn't a tradition passed through אמוראים Amoraim
but actually it was a ברייתא. beraisa. אבא שאול Abba Shaul is
a תנא. tanna. אבא שאול בן אימא מרים אמר בין דלא שבועה
בין דנקי שבועה בין דלא נדר בין דנקי נדר בין דנכסי בין
דנכסי איהו בין הוא בין יורשיו אין משביעין אותה אבל מה אעשה
שהרי אמרו חכמים הבא ליפרע מנכסי יתומים לא יפרע אלא בשבועה.
Abba Shaul ben Ima Miriam amar bein d'la shavua bein d'naki shavua
bein d'la neder bein d'naki neder bein d'nichsai bein d'nichsai ihu bein
hu bein
yorshav ein mashpi'in osah aval mah e'eseh sheharei amru chachamim haba lifra
minichsei yesomim lo yifra ela b'shvuah. Okay, that whole thing was a
ברייתא. beraisa. It wasn't said by רב נחמן אמר שמואל Rav Nachman
amar Shmuel etc. But then here's where רב נחמן אמר שמואל Rav
Nachman amar Shmuel comes in, אמר רב נחמן אמר שמואל הלכה כבן
אימא מרים. Amar Rav Nachman amar Shmuel halachah k'ben Ima Miriam. It's
interesting, not הלכה כאבא שאול, halachah k'Abba Shaul, we rule like the
son of
אימא מרים. Ima Miriam. Maybe him and exactly interesting, right, the presence
of the mother in this discussion. Okay. So that is waiving her
from a שבועה shvuah and now we get to the other שבועה,
shvuah, which we said that the משנה Mishnah was talking about, which
is not the שבועה shvuah of the storekeeper but a other types
of שבועות shvuos that a woman will have to make to her
husband. Okay, let's take a look. הפוגמת כתובתה לא תפרע אלא בשבועה,
ha'pogemes ksuvasah lo tifrah ela b'shvuah, a woman who injures her כתובה,
ksuvah, who cuts into her כתובה, ksuvah, who admits that part of
it has been paid up, needs to make a שבועה. shvuah. עד
אחד מעידה שהיא פרועה, ed echad me'idah sheparuah, or a woman comes
to collect, again, these are divorced let's take the case of divorce
because otherwise we have the whole issue about collecting from heirs, a
woman comes to collect and she's divorced and pay me my my
כתובה, ksuvah, and he says I paid it and she says no
you didn't, so normally of course she'd win, she has the שטר,
shtar, but then one witness actually says no, I saw the husband
pay it up. One witness. לא תפרע
אלא בשבועה, lo tifrah ela b'shvuah, she has to make an oath.
Now for people who know the laws of שבועות shvuos you might
be thinking and the גמרא Gemara is going to say this, that
this sounds like classic
שבועות, shvuos, classic שבועה shvuah of
מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas you
can see it half and the classic
שבועה shvuah No,
I'll let you think about why they're not standard. So standard.
עד אחד ed echad is saying that it's completely paid?
Correct, completely paid. Okay. That's number two.
מעידה Meida means that one עד ed testifies against her?
Well, מעידה על הכתובה. Meida al haktuba. I think it's-
I think it's-
it's not a woman who's testifying.
No,
no, no, no, no, no, no, no. No, it's about it. שהיא
She-hi that- that it, the כתובה kesuba is פרועה. peruah. The feminine
here is on the
כתובה. kesuba. מעידה על אותה, Meida al osah, על הכתובה. al hakesuba.
Okay. מנכסי יתומים מנכסי משועבדים ושלא בפניו לא תפרע אלא בשבועה. Minichsei
yesomim minichsei meshubadim v'shelo b'fanav lo tipara ela bishvua. And here we
have another thing. Anybody, not only a woman, who's coming to collect
from the heirs, okay, and has a debt against the heirs, or
is coming to collect from purchased, or from people that purchased the
land. I lent a thousand dollars to Michael, I got a lien
on his estate, he sold his property to Dove over there, and
now I go and I say, 'I'm executing my lien and I'm
taking over that property.' So you're going to say to me, 'How
do I know you and Michael didn't already- Michael didn't already pay
you up?' So I have to take an oath, right, that he
didn't pay me up. So it's just like the heirs' case. In
both of those cases, you're collecting money from the person who is
not in a position to know whether or not it's been paid
up, right? You understand? Whether it's the heirs or whether it's people
that purchased the property. Okay. מנכסי יתומים נכסי משועבדים ושלא בפניו. Minichsei
yesomim nichsei meshubadim v'shelo b'fanav. Or let's say Michael is just off
in Hawaii. Michael is off there trekking in Machu Picchu and I
figure that this is my- I think- exactly. I'll go to either.
Anyway, and I figure this is my opportunity and I go to
the court and I tell them I need the property, I'm coming
to collect or whatever, okay, and nobody is there so under some
circumstances they'll let me collect even if Michael isn't around, but I'll
have to take an oath that it hasn't been paid because he's
not present to make that claim. Okay. Now, now the משנה Mishna
spells it out. And this משנה, Mishna, you know, sometimes the משניות
Mishnayos are so cryptic. Here this משנה Mishna like over-explains. Let's take
a look at the- I think. Let's take a look at the
משנה. Mishna. הפוגמת כתובתה כיצד? Hapogemes kesubasah keitzad? What's the case of
פוגמת? pogemes? הייתה כתובתה אלף זוז. Hayesa kesubasah elef zuz. The כתובה
kesuba was a thousand dollars. ואמר לה התקבלת כתובתך. V'amar lah hitkabalt
kesubasaich. And he says, 'I paid it off already.' והיא אומרת לא
התקבלתי אלא מנה. V'hi omeres lo hitkabalti ela maneh. 'No, you only
paid me a hundred.' לא תפרע אלא בשבועה. Lo tipara ela bishvua.
She has to take an oath that the nine hundred is still
not paid. עד אחד מעידה שהיא פרועה כיצד? Ed echad meidah she-hi
peruah keitzad? What's the case of one witness? הייתה כתובתה אלף זוז.
Hayesa kesubasah elef zuz. It was a thousand. ואמר לה התקבלת כתובתך.
V'amar lah hitkabalt kesubasaich. And he says, 'You've already been paid it.'
והיא אומרת לא התקבלתי. V'hi omeres lo hitkabalti. 'I haven't been paid
anything.' ועד אחד מעידה שהיא פרועה. V'ed echad meidah she-hi peruah. And
the one witness says it's all been paid. לא תפרע אלא בשבועה.
Lo tipara ela bishvua. She has to take an oath that it
hasn't been paid. מנכסים משועבדים כיצד? Minichasim meshubadim keitzad? How about property
that has a lien on it? Goes a little different order than
the first part of the משנה. Mishna. מכר נכסיו לאחרים. Machar nichasav
l'acherim. We'll get back to it.
Michael there sold his property to other people.
והיא נפרעת מן הלקוחות. V'hi nifraas min halokchos. Or actually it's still-
it's the woman. Okay. So the husband sold and the woman is
coming to collect the כתובה, kesuba, but it would be true also
about any debt. The wife is coming to collect the כתובה kesuba
from the people that purchased the property. לא תפרע אלא בשבועה. Lo
tipara ela bishvua. She has to take an oath that the husband
didn't pay it up. מנכסי יתומים כיצד? Minichsei yesomim keitzad? מת. Meis.
The guy died. והניח נכסיו ליתומים. V'hiniach nichasav l'yesomim. And his property
is left over to his heirs. והיא נפרעת מן היתומים. V'hi nifraas
min hayesomim. She's coming to collect from them. לא תפרע אלא בשבועה.
Lo tipara ela bishvua. She has to make an oath. Wow, you
wonder like, wow, this was all pretty clear at the beginning, so
much explanation. ושלא בפניו כיצד? V'shelo b'fanav keitzad? How about if he's
not around? הלך לו למדינת הים. Halach lo l'medinas hayam. He's over
like I said in Hawaii or Machu Picchu. והיא נפרעת שלא בפניו.
V'hi nifraas shelo b'fanav. אינה נפרעת אלא בשבועה. Eina nifraas ela bishvua.
Okay, she has to take an oath. Very nice. A lot of
explanation. רבי שמעון
אומר כל זמן שהיא תובעת כתובתה היורשין משביעין אותה. Rabbi Shimon omer
kol zman she-hi tova'as kesubasah hayorshin mashbi'in osah. As long as she
is demanding her כתובה, kesuba, the heirs can make her take an
oath. ואם אינה תובעת כתובתה. V'im eina tova'as kesubasah. אין היורשין משביעין
אותה. ein hayorshin mashbi'in osah. When she's not demanding it,
they can't. So it's like if she's not demanding it, of course
they can't. And anyway, what exactly is he saying? So okay, we'll
see about him tomorrow. That's not today. Let's take a look at
the גמרא. Gemara. סבר רמי בר חמא למימר שבועה דאורייתא. Savar Rami
bar Chama l'meimar shvua d'oraisa. Rami bar Chama thought we're talking about
a
biblical שבועה. shvua. דקתני מאתיים D'kasani masayim that she's basically saying
two hundred, וקתני מאה, v'kasani meah, וקמודה לה במאה, u-k'modeh lah b'meah,
and he's conceding a hundred. So it's two hundred and a hundred,
that's a מודה במקצת, modeh b'miktzas, you take an oath.
הוי ליה הודאה במקצת הטענה. Hevei lei hoda'ah b'miktzas hatana. It's conceding
half of the claim or part of the claim. וכל המודה במקצת
הטענה ישבע. V'chol hamodeh b'miktzas hatana yishava. Anybody who concedes part of
a claim has to take an oath. אמר רבא שתי תשובות בדבר.
Amar Rava shtei teshuvos badavar. Rava says there are two responses to
this. Okay, two reasons why you're wrong. חדא דכל הנשבעין שבתורה נשבעין
ולא משלמין. Chada d'chol hanishba'in shebaTorah nishba'in v'lo meshalmin. Says, one is
what is the case of מודה במקצת? modeh b'miktzas? The case of
מודה במקצת modeh b'miktzas is I say David that you owe me
two hundred dollars and
you
concede and
say no- that I can't collect the full 200, you know, it
gets you out of paying the hundred that you say that you're
not obligated for, okay? So that's what the oath does. נשבעין, nishba'in,
you take the oath, ולא משלמין, velo meshalmin, and you don't have
to pay. מה? Mah? נשבע ונפטר, nishba veniftar, right. Okay, by the-
now, by the way, you know, that would be a case where
there's no שטר shtar also, because if there's a שטר shtar you
wouldn't be believed to say you paid a hundred. But there's no
שטר shtar so you're believed and maybe you could've said you paid
it all but you said a hundred, you swear and therefore you
don't have to pay. נשבע ונפטר. nishba veniftar. In this case, A,
there's a שטר shtar which interestingly רבא Rava doesn't even mention, which
is another reason it's different. But let's even bracket that. Here it's
different. Here the woman is coming to collect,
the husband says that he's partially paid. If it were a classic
מודה במקצת, modeh bemiktzat, who would take the oath?
The husband would take the oath and he wouldn't have to pay
the rest. But we're not going to allow that, she's got a
שטר, shtar, right? So what- and actually according to the real הלכה
halacha she's got the כתובה ketubah and according to the real הלכה
halacha we shouldn't believe him at all- well, she actually conceded to
the hundred. He didn't say the hundred. If she said a hundred
he wouldn't be believed at all, she concedes to the hundred. Okay?
But fine, so she conceded to the husband, she's got a שטר,
shtar, so anyway, so there's no classic שבועה. shvuah. Classic שבועה shvuah
is that the guy who concedes- the classic שבועה shvuah is the
guy's making the oath and not paying. Here she's making the oath
and she's collecting. Okay? No, she is receiving, she's
collecting the rest of the 900 that she agreed to. The שטר,
shtar, the שטר shtar indicates that she's been paid part-?
No. The שטר shtar indicates that she's owed the full amount.
So then how does she-?
So מעיקרא דדין, me'ikara dedin, okay, look, let's take a look. מעיקרא
דדין, me'ikara dedin,
whether if the biblical case that there's no שטר, shtar, say you
owe me 200, you say I've already paid a hundred. So מעיקרא
דדין me'ikara dedin you would be like believed, okay, and you'd only-
because I don't have a שטר shtar whatever, you'd only have to
pay a hundred. But because there's some question here, whatever, the שבועה
shvuah makes you take an oath and then you don't pay, but
that allows it to sort of go back to what it would
have been מעיקרא דדין. me'ikara dedin. It doesn't really change the reality,
it just affirms the reality. Okay? In this case, I've got- the
woman's got a שטר, shtar, she concedes that she's been paid a
hundred. If she doesn't concede anything, she collects the full. She concedes
she's been paid a hundred, without any שבועה, shvuah, logically she's got
a שטר, shtar, of course she can collect the full amount, or
of course she can collect the 900 if she concedes she's been
paid a hundred. The שבועה, shvuah, since some question has arisen, the
שבועה shvuah is there to reaffirm and to resolve any lingering questions
and let her go ahead and do what she anyway would have
been able to do which is collect the 900. So in both
cases the שבועה shvuah somehow addresses some questions that have been raised
but doesn't change the basic question of who's being paid. Okay? In
that way they're parallel. But nevertheless, says רבא, Rava, the שבועה דאורייתא
shvuah de'oraisa is to exempt somebody from payment. The person making the
שבועה shvuah is the person getting out of paying. Here she's making
the שבועה shvuah and she's collecting. So it's not a שבועה דאורייתא,
shvuah de'oraisa, okay? Okay.
כל הנשבעים
שבתורה, Kol hanishba'in shebaTorah, נשבעים ולא משלמין. nishba'in velo meshalmin. והיא, Vehi,
and in this case she, נשבעת ונוטלת. nishba'as venoteles. She takes the
שבועה shvuah that she only has been paid a hundred and she
collects the rest. ועוד, Ve'od, and number two, אין נשבעים על כפירת
שעבוד קרקעות. ein nishba'in al kfiras shibud karka'os. This can't be a
שבועה דאורייתא shvuah de'oraisa because דאורייתא de'oraisa you the same- you don't
swear about קרקע karka and you don't swear about something that contains
within it- leans on קרקע. karka. So this, since there's a שטר
shtar that's involved here, okay, besides other reasons like then that serves
as עדות eidus that would otherwise obviate certain שבועה shvuah needs, but
since there's a שטר shtar here what's at stake is- is- is
קרקע, karka, is lien on land. And therefore there's never going to
be a שבועה shvuah when it involves land. Okay, so there's no
שבועה דאורייתא shvuah de'oraisa going on here. So rather this is all
a שבועה דרבנן. shvuah derabbanan.
No שבועה shvuah on land because land's just there, right?
Well, I don't know why, but we learned an exemption about שבועה
shvuah on land. Okay, so therefore there's no שבועה דאורייתא shvuah de'oraisa
and she really should just collect, end of story. אלא אמר רבא,
Ella amar Rava, מדרבנן. miderabbanan. This is rabbinic.
דפרע דייק. Depara dayek. The guy who pay- is paying off his
debt, he knows how much he's paid. He tends to pay attention
to the details.
דמפרע לא דייק Demifra lo dayek is not so necessarily attentive to
that. Okay, so therefore the guy says I know I paid you
in full, right? I mean you could say the guy who's coming
to get out of his debt is willing to- is going to
lie, but okay, I know I paid you in full and she
says no, I only got a hundred. So we imagine it's possible
that there was a scenario that he paid her and she wasn't
so much paying attention, right? Because if you are the one that's
having your debt paid up- if you're the one that's collecting the
money, right, it's not in your interest necessarily to remember... that you've
been paid, right? So therefore, not necessarily you're consciously lying, but you
might have like subconsciously forgotten it, or you certainly didn't pay as
much attention to it as the guy who actually is now free
of his debt. Okay. So, yeah.
I can't remember.
I can't remember if you've paid me up or not.
I betcha I paid.
Exactly. Exactly. So,
okay.
So therefore we say, we don't think anybody is lying. By the
way, this also addresses another problem, which is if you think somebody
is consciously lying, that means that they're intentionally trying to steal from
somebody else. It raises questions that come up in the beginning of
בבא מציעא, Bava Metzia, which is do we say חשוד אממונא חשוד
אשבועתא? chashud amamona chashud ashvuasa? I don't understand, if you're willing to
steal from somebody, then you'd be willing to take a false oath.
We say no actually, you know, people have their own hierarchy of
sins and stealing is one thing, actually swearing falsely to God is
another, which is presumably why people impose oaths because people do think
like that. But once you say the person is willing to consciously
steal, it raises questions how good of the oath is going to
be. Which is why the גמרא Gemara would rather imagine scenarios where
you're not consciously stealing but you somehow are rationalizing or forgetting. And
therefore the oath is going to make you pay closer attention. Exactly.
So here it's saying look, we can imagine scenarios that the husband
knows he's paid and the wife wasn't paying so much attention, and
that you normally don't pay so much as much attention if you're
the one being paid than if you're the one paying.
Okay. So דפרע דייק, depara dayek, the one who's paying pays close
attention, דמיפרע לא דייק, demifre lo dayek, the one who's being paid
does not pay so close attention. ורמי רבנן שבועה עלה, urami rabanan
shvuah alah, so therefore once she concedes that it's been partially paid,
it raises possibilities that maybe it's been fully paid. So the rabbis
imposed a שבועה shvuah on her כי היכי דתידוק, ki heichi detidok,
in order that she should pay now close attention and she should
think one minute, if I have to take an oath about it,
let me really go ahead and, you know, make certain, think through
if I can remember whether or not I've been paid or not.
Yes.
What about this person who's just a witness to this?
עד אחד ed echad then we're going to get to that. That's
the next case. Now we're dealing about one case at a time.
Okay, so now we're dealing about the case...
Why don't they just, why didn't they write something on the כתובה?
ketubah?
They could have. They could have written a receipt or whatever. Okay.
And actually we're going to take a look now at some scenarios.
Let's take a look. Okay. איבעיא להו, iba'ya lehu, so here's the
first question we ask, which is a variation of what David said.
פוגמת כתובתה בעדים מהו. pogemes kesuvosah b'eidim mahu.
Let's say there are witnesses that he paid the first hundred. Maybe
that actually strengthens her case because she can say yeah, whatever you
paid, you paid and you got a receipt or there were witnesses
but that's one hundred, it's not the other nine hundred. Okay. So
מהו, mahu, what do we say... אם איתא דפרע בעדים הוה פרע.
im issa depara b'eidim hava para.
Do we say now we see that when he pays up he
would have ensured that there were witnesses, because he ensured there were
witnesses to the first hundred. So if he paid the other nine
hundred there would have been witnesses or there would have been a
receipt. And since there isn't, no need for a שבועה, shvuah, we
believe her. Okay. That's a variation of what David was saying. או
דילמא, o dilma, or do we say, אישתמוטי אישתמי ליה, ishtamuti ishtami
leh, it just so happened when he paid the first hundred there
were people around that saw it, but that doesn't prove that he
didn't pay the other nine hundred just because he doesn't have witnesses.
So the presence of witnesses or of a receipt on part of
it doesn't sort of prove that he certainly didn't pay the rest.
It's still possible he did and she would still have to take
her שבועה. shvuah.
But that's just, that's just people throwing around.
Yeah, people chanced to be there, happened to be there. תא שמע,
ta shma, come and hear, כל הנשבעין שבתורה נשבעין ולא משלמין. kol
hanishba'in shebaTorah nishba'in velo meshalmin. Everybody so this is a משנה, Mishnah,
all the people who take oaths in the תורה, Torah, they do
it and they get out, which is what רבא Rava said, and
they don't pay. So a תורה Torah oath is when you're exempt
from payment. ואלו נשבעין ונוטלין, ve'elu nishba'in venotlin, and the following are
rabbinic oaths where you can take a שבועה shvuah and collect, that
they actually allowed there were some question and they and they said
take a שבועה shvuah and that will actually allow us to trust
you to allow you to actually extract money from somebody else, which
is a חידוש, chiddush, right? Because normally we say if you want
to extract money you need real proof. But there were certain types
that the rabbis allowed there to be a שבועה shvuah to back
up a statement to actually take money from somebody else. What are
they? השכיר, hasachir, the hired hand. Basically the laborer says you didn't
pay me my wages and you said yes I did, so they
actually came to the defense of the of the you know of
the laborer. So the hired hand,
הנגזל, hanigzal, somebody who has been somebody you know robbed from somebody
else and it's clear that he robbed from the person but there's
no question about what exact property he took. So the person that's
been robbed can take an oath to say what was that property
that was stolen from him. והנחבל, vehanechbal, somebody that's been injured by
somebody else. Personal injury. Okay now there what what's the doubt? You
look at the body you see how much he's been injured. Okay
but the question is that it's not totally clear this person injured.
Here I was I was in a house you saw me walk
into this house all looking you know nice and totally in good
shape and then Michael came into the house afterwards and then Michael
left looking in good shape and then I left all black and
blue. Okay so nobody actually saw Michael beat me up. Okay, now
you see how much he's been injured, okay, but the question is
is that it's not totally clear this person injured. Here I was,
I was in a house, you saw me walk into this house
all looking, you know, nice and totally in good shape, and then
Michael came into the house afterwards, and then Michael left looking in
good shape, and then I left all black and blue, okay, so
nobody actually saw Michael beat me up and then Michael says, "What
are you talking about? You tripped over a chair," okay, but in
that scenario, I can take the oath that Michael was the one
that beat me up and I can collect from Michael. That's a
נחבל. nechbal.
Where you can take an oath that, like, either way? Like, you
know there's let's say
you can't take the oath.
No, no, you take an oath that, you know, the owner of
the property left his whatever it is.
Oh, no, that's an interesting question about whether I don't know. It's
specifically about חבלה chavalah between people.
ושכנגדו חשוד על השבועה. ve'she'kenegdo chashud al ha'shvuah. Now, let's say Michael
here has to take an oath that, I say you owe me
two hundred dollars, he says I already paid a hundred, so he's
a מודה במקצת. modeh be'miktzat. The הלכה halacha is he should take
an oath and he should be exempt from the hundred that he
claims. The only problem is, is that, sorry Michael, we have some
evidence that Michael actually sometimes takes false oaths. Not true. Okay, so
he's נחשד. nechshad. So what good is it going to do to
have him take an oath that he paid up the hundred? We
know that he's not trustworthy about that. So in that case, we
say, okay, I'll take the oath that he owes me the full
two hundred and I'll go ahead and collect. Okay, so instead of
him taking an oath and getting out of, you know, and only
paying a hundred, since he can't take the oath, I'll take the
oath and my statement will be believed and I'll be able to
collect the full two hundred.
So he is not allowed to access the מודה במקצת modeh be'miktzat
as it were. You can take the oath instead.
Right, he doesn't have, right, exactly. Okay, so the שבועה shvuah doesn't
protect his statement. Since he can't make it, I'll make the שבועה
shvuah and it'll back my statement.
וחנווני על פנקסו, ve'chanvani al pinkaso, and the storekeeper by his ledger.
Basically I tell the storekeeper, you know, go ahead and give my
פועלים, poalim, give them, you know, bread and eggs and whatever, and
that'll be towards their fee, and toward, I mean, towards, you know,
their salary. And then I didn't demand anybody get any receipts or
evidence or whatever. And the פועלים poalim come to me and they
say he never gave it to us. And he comes to me
and he says I gave it to them. And nobody has any
proof or whatever. So basically I owe now both my storekeeper and
my פועלים. poalim. I gotta pay them both. Okay. And as long
as the storekeeper has to take an oath that he did what
he was supposed to do. Okay.
Is that also an oath that's sworn and?
Yeah, right. והפוגם... ve'hapogem... well,
no, that's going back to the שכיר. sachir. והפוגם... ve'hapogem...
I mean, I don't know in that case. Okay, because I'm not
making a ודאי טענה, vadai ta'anah, right. Anyway, והפוגם שטרו שלא בעדים.
ve'hapogem shtaro she'lo ve'edim. Here's why we brought this whole thing in.
Somebody who basically says that his,
that the שטר shtar has been paid up. Now it's not just
about the woman. It's any case of somebody that concedes that part
of a debt has been paid up with a שטר, shtar, that
he has to take an oath that the rest of it has
not been paid. But it specifically says that the part has been
paid without witnesses. There were no witnesses to see the first part's
been paid. Okay, and that's, the גמרא Gemara says that answers our
question. שלא בעדים she'lo ve'edim in, when there were no witnesses to
the first payment, then ironically you have to take an oath because
maybe the rest has been paid as well. But presumably בעדים be'edim
לא, lo, if there are witnesses to the first half of the
payment... He doesn't have to swear? Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara
is going to respond. Then you don't have to take an oath
because then I could say if you had paid the full amount,
where are the witnesses on the second half? There's only witnesses on
the first payment. If you say there was a second payment, where
are the witnesses? I don't have to take an oath. So that
seems to say you do not. But now the גמרא Gemara says,
no, the opposite. לא מיבעיא קאמר. lo mibaya ka'amar. Maybe it goes
without saying. לא מיבעיא בעדים. lo mibaya be'edim. It goes without saying
that if there are witnesses that you paid the first amount, ודאי
צריכה שבועה, vadai tzrichah shvuah, then I certainly have to take an
oath because then it's really concrete evidence that part has been paid,
so maybe the rest has been paid. אבל שלא בעדים, aval she'lo
ve'edim, if there's no witnesses that you made the first payment, אימא
תהוי כמשיב אבידה, eima tehavi kemeshiv aveidah, then I'll say the fact
that I'm conceding that a first payment has been made even though
there's no evidence of it, so I'm like giving
you a lost object. Like, I could have easily have claimed that
nothing's been paid. The woman's saying this. ותישתקיל בלא שבועה, ve'tishtakeil belo
shvuah, she should be able to collect without a שבועה. shvuah. So
it's one thing if there's concrete evidence that part of it has
been paid, I have to make an oath that the rest has
not. But if it's just your claim that you've paid it all
and I concede that a hundred's been paid, I didn't have to
concede anything.
That's the מיגו. migo.
So it's like a מיגו. migo. Nevertheless, אימא תהוי כמשיב אבידה בלא
שבועה קא משמע לן eima tehavi kemeshiv aveidah belo shvuah ka mashma
lan that you have to. So we don't know the answer. We
don't know if there's witnesses, certainly if there's no witnesses, the woman
has to make an oath that the rest has not been paid
if she concedes that part of it has. If there's witnesses that
part of it has, does that make it better or
worse that she would still have to make an oath in that
case? איבעיא להו. ibaia lehu. Let's just get to the two dots.
They asked the following question. הפוגמת כתובתה פחות פחות משתי פרוטות מהו.
hapogemet ketubatah pachos pachos mishtei prutos mahu. If somebody concedes partial pennies,
what's the story? Now what does that mean? One day she says
I concede a half a penny, the next day I concede another
half? No, the way רש״י Rashi says it is she does the
חשבון. cheshbon. She takes out her ledger and she says, okay, look,
here's your record of payments. On this day you paid twenty-three dollars...
And this day you paid another seventy-five dollars and sixteen cents. Okay,
and she goes and she tabulates the whole thing, all with dollars
and cents. It's a very exacting record that she has. And now
we're going to say, oh maybe you forgot and he paid off
the rest. Like it's very clear she's keeping a very precise record
of the payments. Right? It's- it's in pennies. I don't know, that's
the way רש''י Rashi reads. I'm just telling you what רש''י Rashi
reads, okay? That's the way רש''י Rashi reads it. So in that
case if she's got a precise record, do we really think that
she doesn't remember whether he's paid the
rest? Okay, מי אמרינן כיוון דקדייקא כולי האי, mi amrinan keivun dekadaika
kulei hai, since she's so precise to be counting up the pennies,
קושטא קאמרה, kushta ka'amrah, she's clearly telling the truth. או דילמא, o
dilma, or do we say, ערומי קמערימה, arumei kama'arimah,
she's really a- really a good liar. This way they'll believe me.
I'll- I'll say it's twenty-three dollars and seventy-four cents, so I won't
have to take a שבועה, shvuah, you know, it's a good way
to get out of it. תיקו, teiku, we don't know. Okay, of
course the irony is if she totally wanted to lie she could
say you didn't pay me anything. But again, you know, but this
maybe gives her more credibility. She concedes it and she concedes with
the dollars and pennies, so she'll say, I'll both get the credibility
and I won't make the שבועה. shvuah. So we don't know. איבעיא
להו, iba'ya lehu, פוחתת כתובתה מהו? pochashes kesuvasah mahu?
What about if she doesn't say it's been partially paid off, she
actually says it never was the full amount. Okay, the כתובה kesuvah
on the face of it says a thousand dollars, but she says,
yeah, that's what we wrote in the כתובה, kesuvah, but between us
we agreed that it was really only a two hundred dollar כתובה.
kesuvah. Okay, so I'm not conceding that you paid anything, I'm just
conceding that the amount was really less. So since the whole reason
we make her שבועה shvuah is once part has been paid, maybe
the rest has been paid, here it's not been paid at all.
She's just conceding that it's not the full amount. So let's believe
her and let's entitle her to collect what she does say it's
worth without a שבועה. shvuah. מי אמרינן, mi amrinan, do we say,
היינו פוגמת, hainu pogemes, it's the exact same, it says one thing
and she's saying it's really a smaller amount? או דילמא, o dilma,
no, פוגמת מודה במקצת, pogemes modeh bimiktzas, a פוגמת pogemes she concedes
part of the claim that there's been a partial payment. If there's
been a partial payment, maybe there's been a full payment. הא לא
קמודה במקצת, ha lo kamodeh bimiktzas, she's not conceding any payment's been
made. תא שמע, ta shema, פוחתת תפרע שלא בשבועה. pochashes tifrah shelo
bishvuah. If somebody says that it was a lesser amount, then she
can collect without a שבועה. shvuah. כיצד, keitzad, what's a case of
conceding of a lesser amount, not a partial payment but a lesser
amount? הייתה כתובתה אלף זוז, haisah kesuvasah elef zuz, on the face
of it it says
a thousand dollars. ואמר לה, ve'amar lah, התקבלת כתובתיך, hiskabalt kesuvasayich, I've
paid it all up. והיא אומרת, vehi omeres, לא התקבלתי, lo hiskabalti,
I have not- you didn't pay one red cent. ואין אלא מנה,
ve'ein ela maneh, but I concede that it really isn't a thousand
dollar כתובה, kesuvah, it's really a hundred dollar כתובה. kesuvah. But you
didn't pay a penny. We- we- we just- we made a deal
between us that we'll write a big amount, but you really won't
have to pay that amount. Okay, so in that case, תפרע שלא
בשבועה, tifrah shelo bishvuah, she can collect the hundred dollars without a
שבועה. shvuah. So now the גמרא gemara says, במה גביא, bamah gavya,
I don't understand, what's she collecting with? בהאי שטרא, behai shtra, with
this שטר? shtar? האי שטרא חספא בעלמא הוא, hai shtra chispa be'alma
hu, it's a piece of pottery, it's toilet paper, meaning it's not-
right? It- it says a thousand, she's conceding that it's false, so
why is it like it's- why is it like it has any
validity at all?
The מיגו migo would be that she would be entitled to the
hundred no matter what, though, right?
Well- yeah- that's- that's true about תנאי בית דין, tnai beis din,
but then- but if it's no שטר, shtar, he'd be believed to
say that it's פרוע. parua. The only reason he's not believed to
say it's fully פרוע parua is because she has a שטר, shtar,
but the שטר shtar is a false שטר. shtar. So- so the
גמרא gemara says,
אמר רבא בריה דרבא, amar rava breih de'rava, באומרת אמנה הייתה לי
ביני לבינו, be'omeres amanah haisah li beini leveino, there's trust between me
and him. Okay, so it's not like I'm saying it's a false
שטר. shtar. No, at the wedding we wrote a thousand, we got
the עדים. eidim. I don't know if you've ever been in some
Sephardi weddings, like they write- like the תוספת tosefes is like a
million dollars or something. Well, we wrote what we wrote, did we
want to make the parents happy? They wanted to see he was
promising me a big amount. So we wrote it, we עדים eidim
signed it. Technically it's a good שטר. shtar. Technically he's obligated to
me the thousand dollars, but we agreed that I would only collect
a hundred. I agreed to not collect nine hundred of it. Okay,
so the שטר shtar is a good שטר, shtar, but I conceded
I wouldn't collect it all. And in that case, even though she's
not collecting the full amount of the שטר, shtar, she's not saying
that anything's been paid, so she doesn't have to make a שבועה.
shvuah. All right, we will end with that.
Okay, yeah.